<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the parish-church of St. Chad's in  Shrewsbury, March 5, 1694/5 being the funeral day of our most gracious sovereign Queen Mary / by Thomas Dawes.</title>
            <author>Dawes, Thomas, 1652?-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24877</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08630357</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08630357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41504</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41504)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1255:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the parish-church of St. Chad's in  Shrewsbury, March 5, 1694/5 being the funeral day of our most gracious sovereign Queen Mary / by Thomas Dawes.</title>
                  <author>Dawes, Thomas, 1652?-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F.C. for Gabriel Rogers, and are to be sold by John Whitlock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A semon preach'd upon the funeral of the Queen.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41504:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the PARISH-CHURCH OF St. <hi>Chad</hi>'s in <hi>SHREWSB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY, March</hi> 5.1694/5 BEING THE Funeral Day <hi>of our Moſt Gracious Sovereign</hi> Queen Mary.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS DAWES.</hi> B. D Miniſter of the Church of St. <hi>MARY</hi> in the ſaid Town.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>F. C.</hi> for <hi>Gabriel Rogers</hi> in <hi>Shrewsbury;</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>John Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41504:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41504:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Samuel Adderton <hi>Eſq;</hi> Mayor, And other the Members of the Corporation; Together with the Gentry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Town of <hi>Shrewsbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHen my Service was deſired to aſſiſt on the much Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Occaſion of our <hi>Good Queens Funeral Day,</hi> I confeſs, I thought the Solemnity ſo agreeable to my own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reſpect and Duty, that as a Son of the Church, I could not well refuſe. But when afterwards, your Requeſts proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much farther than I had reaſon to expect, and your Importunity would not eaſily admit of any Excuſe; I am more unwillingly forced thus a ſecond time to
<pb facs="tcp:41504:3"/>Gratifie you by appearing more publick than I intended; which I am ſenſible might as well have been ſpared, were it not for your Serious Regard to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Loſs, in which I own a real Concern, and, in ſo doing, am ſure to approve my ſelf more acceptably, as I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Affectionate Humble Servant, <hi>THO. DAWES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41504:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Chron. Chap. 35. latter part of the 24 v.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>—He Dyed, and was Buried in one of the Sepulchres of his Fathers: and all <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> mourned for <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>COuld our Grief be always hid, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly conceal'd, we Chriſtians need no ſtronger Antidote, than that of our Religion, as it teaches us Submiſſion to all Gods Providences, when they look unfavoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to our Temporal Intereſts. Thus we have often in ſilence put our hands upon our mouths, and with Reluctancy ſtop'd th' erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and clamour of many of our Sorrows, and would have done ſo now, and ſtoop'd parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly under our Fate, which is our preſſure very ſenſible, but that our Loſs is ſo confeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great; and our Paſſions, in their reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41504:4"/>more than uſually high, laviſh, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ungovernable. All Afflictions, we find by woful experience, are not equal, and of the ſame ſize, and magnitude. 'Tis alas! more than once, we have loſt a Dear Friend, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtood very nigh our tender heart, and when Dead, we could not but Lament; but ſeldom ſo loud as now, when we are forced to exchange our Patience for our Pious Sorrow; we Weep, and mean it ſo, as we think it is our Religious Duty to bewail.—I need not name th'Occaſion, when I ſee here all Faces gather <hi>Blackneſs,</hi> and ſtrive with concern zealouſly to augment the ſerious Pomp of our <hi>Funeral La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation.</hi> We have loſt; but could our Loſs be utter'd! I am not able equally to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs your <hi>Grief,</hi> who want Words, ſo many, to expreſs my own.</p>
            <p>But here, this Day, when all the Engliſh Nation <hi>Mourns,</hi> as we do, and the vaſt Deluge of our <hi>Tears</hi> ſwells ſo univerſally wide, that they waft a far of our <hi>Sorrow,</hi> as they roal from ſhore to ſhore and drown our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours too, as well as we; how can we refrain! Let this day paſs ever then for a <hi>Day of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi> Yet tho' I cannot poſſibly excuſe your
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41504:4"/>
               <hi>Mourning;</hi> give me leave to inquire a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Nature of our <hi>Common Diſtreſs,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to juſtifie our <hi>Grief;</hi> as approveable to all Mankind; and to ſhew how 'tis not only a violent, haſty Tempeſt of our ſenſual Paſſion, but a calm, deliberate, ſound reſentment (if our Sorrow be capable of ſo much Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) which has invited us hither to Condole together the <hi>Death</hi> of our <hi>Good Queen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this end I have pitch'd upon one of the Greateſt <hi>Inſtances</hi> in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Jewiſh Church, Joſiah</hi> by name, famous for <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> with a real Zeal for the <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of the true <hi>God;</hi> which is all indeed, beſides what is leſs (<hi>Luſtre</hi> and <hi>Magnificence</hi>) which raiſes, and ſupports the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Majeſty.</hi> We find here his Good Subjects of all ſorts, aſſembled, 'tis like, as well as we, all over the Land (<hi>Town</hi> and <hi>Countrey</hi>) to <hi>Mourn and Lament his Funeral. He Dyed, and was Buried</hi> (ſays the Text) <hi>in one of the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres of his Fathers</hi> (i. e. in the Sepulchres of the <hi>Kings</hi>) <hi>and all</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>mourn'd for</hi> Joſiah.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Royal Perſon</hi> here ſpoke of, and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented</hi> was a <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> incluſive of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41504:5"/>
               <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Benjamin:</hi> which were the only two, which remained whole of the <hi>Twelve;</hi> all the reſt (excepting ſome few perſons) having gone off, generally long before from the true <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as then 'twas into <hi>Idolatry</hi> at the frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent Inſtigation of a wicked <hi>King Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am;</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin: and not long after, into <hi>remedileſs Captivity,</hi> under the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> of the <hi>Heathen</hi> their Neighbours. There had been ſome <hi>Good</hi> and many <hi>Bad Kings,</hi> 'till the ſucceſſion of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> whoſe Government commenc'd about 385 years, after the Death of King <hi>David</hi> the ſecond in order, but yet the firſt of their Religious Kings. <hi>Joſiah</hi> was a <hi>Good Son,</hi> of a very <hi>Bad Father, Amon,</hi> who was the Son of <hi>Manaſſeh. Manaſſeh</hi> went off, and apoſtatiz'd from his Religion, and turn'd a profeſs'd <hi>Idolater.</hi> He did evil after the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations</hi> of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> Built <hi>High places</hi> and <hi>Altars</hi> to <hi>Baal, &amp;c.</hi> made his Son to paſs through the Fire, a cruel bloody <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> or rather here a kind of <hi>Luſtration,</hi> to the Idol <hi>Molech;</hi> ſo prevalent is <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Bigot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> even to the looſing the ſtrongeſt Bond of Natural affection. You'll ſee his Hiſtory more at large here (<hi>Cap.</hi> 33. &amp; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.) where
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41504:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>'tis ſaid <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>He</hi> (Amon) <hi>did evil in the ſight of the Lord, as did</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>his Father.</hi> They were both (<hi>Father and Son</hi>) immediately deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended of that <hi>Good King Hezekiah,</hi> who did much for the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the true <hi>God,</hi> and confiding in his <hi>Religious Integrity,</hi> and the favour, and protection of th' <hi>Almighty,</hi> he manfully withſtood the <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> of <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib,</hi> (here <hi>Cap.</hi> 32. &amp; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18) There paſſed 56 years betwixt the Reign of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah;</hi> all which time the <hi>Government</hi> was wretchedly Debauch'd with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and other grievous <hi>Abominations,</hi> for which <hi>Mannaſſeh</hi> is drove out of his Kingdom, into a <hi>Forreign Land:</hi> From all which you will eaſily gueſs, there was more than a little for our <hi>Religious Prince</hi> to do, when he came to the <hi>Throne,</hi> and intended a <hi>Thro-Reformation;</hi> and the the truth is, He did not Delay; but ſet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently about it, with all his power; which will better appear, if we conſider, how <hi>He</hi> came very young to the Crown (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. and here <hi>Cap.</hi> 34.) but what he wanted in Age, He made up in <hi>Virtue.</hi> He was (ſays <hi>Joſephus</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſpoſition, and naturally inclin'd to <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41504:6"/>and <hi>good Life,</hi> which is a mighty Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Young Prince, agreeable to what the <hi>Antient Scripture</hi> ſays of him, from whence the Antiquary took it.</p>
            <p>When this <hi>Godly man</hi> was but 20 years old, <hi>He</hi> began to purge <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (<hi>Town,</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> as I ſaid) from the <hi>High Places</hi> of <hi>Idolatrous Worſhip;</hi> he brake down the <hi>Altars</hi> of <hi>Baalam</hi> (in the plural) ſignifying the many <hi>Falſe Gods</hi> they Worſhipp'd; and in the 26 year of his <hi>Life,</hi> and the 18 of his <hi>Reign, He</hi> and <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> whom he truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; purges and repairs the <hi>Temple.</hi> It appears they had Built an <hi>Heathen Altar</hi> there; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo many other in the <hi>Royal City,</hi> and <hi>Regions</hi> adjoyning (as you will read here in their ſtory) which he viſited <hi>perſonally</hi> for the greateſt part, and utterly Deſtroy'd; not omitting the ſearch even of their <hi>private Houſes,</hi> ſo to root out ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually all <hi>Heathen Abominations</hi> out of the <hi>Land,</hi> the accurſed object of <hi>God</hi>'s otherwiſe implacable Hatred and Diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hilkiah,</hi> hy a ſpecial order from the <hi>King,</hi> ſearching into the <hi>Ruines</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> (not totally Deſtroy'd till afterward, in <hi>Zedekiah</hi>'s
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41504:6"/>time, but too ſadly Decay'd by the many Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious abuſes of the <hi>Idol-Prieſts</hi>) he chances to light upon an <hi>old Authentick Copy</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> which he found Buried in the <hi>Rubbiſh,</hi> in ſome cloſe part of the Building which was neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; 'tis like, that was the only true <hi>Copy</hi> they had left: probably all the reſt being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of their hands, and <hi>Burnt,</hi> (or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe effectually Deſtroy'd) by a cruel <hi>Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> it being uſual with the <hi>Heathen</hi> ſo to do, as ſince with a Religion, as <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> for ſo much as <hi>they,</hi> tho' call'd <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Catholick.</hi> 'Twas ſo before, and in the <hi>Empire</hi> of <hi>Julian th' Apoſtate,</hi> when the <hi>Holy Books</hi> were gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all imaginable Induſtry of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and Deſtroy'd, to make room for the <hi>Lying O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and their <hi>Idol Gods.</hi> But not ſo totally Deſtroy'd then; nor here in <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s time, nowithſtanding the <hi>Dotage</hi> of <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hilkiah</hi> having thus found the <hi>Book,</hi> and ſhew'd it to the <hi>good King, He</hi> entertains it with great <hi>Reverence;</hi> and cauſes it to be read in the ears of the <hi>People,</hi> to teach 'em (what they had forgot, be ſure in too great a meaſure) the true <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> By this, and other ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41504:7"/>his <hi>Religious</hi> pious Arts, he brought back again the <hi>Holy Worſhip,</hi> and the <hi>People,</hi> the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers to the <hi>Temple;</hi> which they, with their Forefathers, had ſo long forſaken: having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready notoriouſly diſgrac'd their <hi>Profane Altars,</hi> by <hi>Burning</hi> the <hi>Bones</hi> of their <hi>Idolatrous Prieſts</hi> upon 'em; (ſome of 'em, that were Dead; all the reſt, but thoſe he ſlew, having fled, and and made their eſcape ('tis like) upon this ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Revolution: and left thus ingloriouſly their <hi>Temples,</hi> and their <hi>Gods,</hi> all a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to the <hi>Zeal</hi> of good <hi>Joſiah;</hi> who put a <hi>fatal</hi> period to their ſenſleſs, tho' cruel <hi>Devotion. Manaſſeh</hi> and <hi>Amon</hi> now dead; their great <hi>Patrons</hi> (it having been till then the <hi>Kings Religion</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! The <hi>Idol</hi> ſtoops, and tamely reſign'd it's feign'd <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> and owns a <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was this any ſuddain ſtart, and heat of Paſſion in <hi>Joſiah,</hi> (as Zeal is too apt to extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagance in unwary hands) for we find here, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>He</hi> had purg'd, and reſtor'd the <hi>Temple, He</hi> deliberately, with the joynt adviſe, and conſent of his <hi>People,</hi> who were by this time return'd to their <hi>right <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings,</hi> in the 18 year of his <hi>Happy Reign,</hi> (already named) <hi>Joſiah</hi> ſends, and proclaims a <hi>Paſſover</hi> to the <hi>Lord;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41504:7"/>which he celebrates, on ſuch a ſplendid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with ſo much <hi>magnificence,</hi> in honour of the true <hi>God,</hi> that the <hi>Tale</hi> and number of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> is almoſt incredible, which made ſuch an extraordinary ſolemn <hi>figure,</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that never was the like <hi>Feſtivity</hi> in ſuch <hi>Glorious Preparation,</hi> ſeen among them. 'Tis deſcrib'd at large here (<hi>Cap.</hi> 35.) <hi>there was never held ſuch a Paſsover from the Days of the</hi> Judges, <hi>which judged</hi> Iſrael, <hi>&amp;c. i. e.</hi> never ſuch an one before, ſince the <hi>Beginning</hi> of their <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> which was a joyful ſight (we may well think) at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> where 'till that time, the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> had lain ſo long neglected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'twas ſo magnificent that (I obſerve) <hi>Joſephus</hi> their <hi>Antiquary,</hi> ſeems ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at it; as tho' it reflected upon the <hi>Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the <hi>Devotion</hi> of the <hi>Antient Church;</hi> and excuſes it thus (<hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>Ant.</hi>) the reaſon (ſays he) why there was no ſuch <hi>Feſtivity</hi> from the days of <hi>Samuel</hi> (mention'd here, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.18.) was becauſe in thoſe early Times, all things were perform'd in exact complyance to <hi>Moſes Ritual,</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> then on foot; tho' the Levitical Law left place for <hi>Free-will-Offerings;</hi> and ſuch (according to <hi>Joſephus</hi>)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41504:8"/>was a great part of this <hi>Celebrated Paſſover</hi> of <hi>Joſiah.</hi> Which therefore is a ſingular argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>Good Kings</hi> more than ordinary <hi>Devotion:</hi> and his <hi>Zeal</hi> in promoting the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> And hence 'tis we read, (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.25.) <hi>And like unto him there was no King, before him, that turn'd to the Lord with all his heart,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neither after him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe there any like him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, <hi>Joſiah</hi> was one, purpoſely rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up of <hi>God</hi> for this <hi>Noble Deſign.</hi> It was <hi>Prophetically</hi> foretold 360 <hi>years,</hi> and more (ſays the Jew) in the <hi>Reign of</hi> Jeroboam, that thus it ſhould be: (1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.2.) <hi>Behold a Child ſhall be born to the Houſe of</hi> David, Joſiah <hi>by name, and upon Thee</hi> (i. e. the Altar at <hi>Bethel,</hi> which the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Nehat</hi> had then newly ſet up) <hi>ſhall he offer the Prieſts of the High-Places, &amp;c.</hi> and it fell out exactly (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.15, 16.)</p>
            <p>You ſee then, how for this very end, in a long courſe of Providence, <hi>Joſiah</hi> was raiſed of <hi>God</hi> to Root out by his means, and to Deſtroy <hi>Idolatry</hi> from out of <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as much as was left of the foregoing <hi>Captivity.</hi> Such, and ſo remarkable was this <hi>Pious Kings</hi> ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Devotion!</hi> and to the great <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41504:8"/>of all his Subjects, (but ſome, who had little or no <hi>Religion;</hi> and others, that hanker'd after that <hi>He</hi> had Deſtroy'd by the will of <hi>God</hi>) <hi>He Reigned</hi> 31 <hi>years;</hi> and Liv'd in the whole 40 bating one, proſperous in <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> and then very unfortunately, by the inceſſant Provocation of the <hi>Crying ſins</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> (as <hi>Huldah</hi> the Propheteſs at that time foretold) <hi>God</hi> was finally reſolv'd to puniſh very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly; as <hi>He</hi> did in the enſuing <hi>Captivity,</hi> which laſted no leſs while than 70 long years, under the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> (as <hi>Jeremy</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> years after <hi>Joſiah's</hi> Death) unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, I ſay. <hi>He</hi> makes War againſt <hi>Necho</hi> the <hi>Aegyptian King;</hi> who was upon his March a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt th' <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> denies him paſſage thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Country, imagining ('tis like) he was a going up againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> when (it ſeems, as he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd by his <hi>Embaſſaders</hi>) <hi>He</hi> intended no ſuch thing. But <hi>Joſiah</hi> liſtned not; and raſhly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes <hi>Himſelf</hi> upon the Borders, in the <hi>Valley</hi> of <hi>Megiddon;</hi> where <hi>He</hi> is mortally wounded by an <hi>Aegyptian Archer,</hi> as <hi>He</hi> rode in his <hi>Chariot;</hi> thereupon carry'd back to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where <hi>He Dyes.</hi> This <hi>Good King,</hi> ſo neceſſary to the <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs</hi> of his <hi>People,</hi> which Dyes together with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41504:9"/>
               <hi>Him.</hi> Their Dreadful <hi>Calamity</hi> was only De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd till his <hi>Death;</hi> inaſmuch as <hi>his</hi> Heart was tender, and <hi>He</hi> humbled <hi>Himſelf</hi> before <hi>God</hi> (here <hi>Cap.</hi> 34 27, 28.) He <hi>Dyes</hi> at his <hi>Royal City, and was Buried in the Sepulchres</hi> of the Kings, <hi>his Fathers, and all</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem (the whole Kingdom) <hi>mourned for</hi> Joſiah.</p>
            <p>And, no doubt, a ſad <hi>Mourning</hi> 'twas: The <hi>Loſs</hi> of ſo <hi>Good</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> and at ſuch a time, when (we muſt think) the <hi>Eyes,</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> of all his <hi>People</hi> were upon Him!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> upon this ſad occaſion, <hi>Weep'd,</hi> and penn'd a <hi>Mournful Elogy;</hi> emphatically a <hi>Black Book of Lamentation;</hi> in ſuch a deep, natural, racy ſtrein, that it weeps yet afreſh to every eye that reads it; ſee there (<hi>Cap.</hi> 4.20.) <hi>The Breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord was taken in their Pits, of whom we ſaid, under His ſhadow, we ſhall live among the Heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo famous was this <hi>Solemn Mourning</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that about an 100 years after, where the <hi>Prophet Zechary</hi> foretells of the <hi>Coming</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of the Meſſiah,</hi> and the fearful <hi>Deſolation,</hi> which ſhould, at that time, befal the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the <hi>Total Devaſtation</hi> of their <hi>Second Temple,</hi> and their <hi>City,</hi> with their <hi>whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41504:9"/>by the <hi>Romans.</hi> He could not expreſs their <hi>Sorrow</hi> to greater advantage; than by this <hi>Deplorable inſtance</hi> of the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Good Joſiah.</hi> (<hi>Cap.</hi> 12.11.) <hi>In that day</hi> (ſays he) <hi>There ſhall be a great Mourning in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>as the Mourning of</hi> Haddadrimmon, <hi>in the valley of</hi> Megiddon: which is the <hi>Mourning</hi> of the <hi>Text</hi> here.</p>
            <p>And ſuch was the <hi>Jews</hi> eſtimation of their <hi>Great Loſs,</hi> and Misfortune; that 'twas not only a little time, which once they ſet apart to this their <hi>Mourning;</hi> but they made it an <hi>Anniverſary Faſt,</hi> in their <hi>Generations,</hi> by an <hi>Ordinance</hi> for ever, (in the <hi>v.</hi> next after the <hi>Text.</hi>) From whence it would ſeem, <hi>The Book of Lamentations</hi> was the <hi>Form</hi> of their <hi>publick</hi> yearly <hi>Humiliation,</hi> upon this account. So great the <hi>Loſs,</hi> and ſo great the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> of this <hi>unhappy</hi> people!</p>
            <p>And yet not ſo great, but in good ſence of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance,</hi> it may become a <hi>Pattern</hi> of ours now. 'Tis confeſſed (Bleſſed be our <hi>Good God,</hi> who in Judgment remembers Mercy) our Circumſtances are not, in Proſpect, ſo Deplorable, as theirs were. The proud King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> has not yet ſet his foot upon our <hi>Land,</hi> nor <hi>Burnt</hi> our <hi>Church,</hi> and made us his <hi>Captives;</hi> nor, we hope, ever will ſo long as we have <hi>God,</hi> and a <hi>Good King</hi> our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors;</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:41504:10"/>who is (as <hi>Joſiah</hi> was) an implacable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary to his, our <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> Enemies. The <hi>Glorious Champion</hi> of our <hi>Holy War;</hi> The Greateſt <hi>Patron</hi> of all the <hi>Proteſtant Churches,</hi> Born indeed the <hi>Son of War;</hi> whoſe <hi>Sword,</hi> (invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as 'tis) gliſters <hi>aſtoniſhment</hi> in the Hearts of thoſe, who are only great in this, that they have the honour to fall under the reſiſtleſs ſtroke of his <hi>Victorious Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Royal Great Soul,</hi> untaught to yield to any other <hi>Adverſity</hi> (to ſhew <hi>He</hi> had an <hi>Heart</hi> of <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> tender as his <hi>Religion</hi> is) <hi>Wept</hi> over the <hi>Royal Aſhes</hi> of his <hi>Deareſt Conſort,</hi> our <hi>Good Queen Mary.</hi> Nor was this any light, faint, tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtricture of his inward <hi>Sorrow.</hi> His indelible <hi>Piety,</hi> ſo deeply rooted in his <hi>Breaſt,</hi> ſunk him down low in this his <hi>Affliction;</hi> as low, as 'tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> could. Behold here a <hi>Brave Glorious Conſtellation</hi> of the greateſt <hi>Fortitude,</hi> and the greateſt <hi>Love!</hi> ſuch an one ſeldom, never ſhone before in our <hi>Hemiſphere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How then ſhall we Subjects Diſpenſe with this <hi>Free Subſidy,</hi> yet naturally a <hi>Debt</hi> of our <hi>Funeral Lamentation?</hi> unleſs we have in this Diſtance to <hi>Her</hi> much <hi>Lamented Death,</hi> ſpent all our Stock al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and in ſo doing exhauſted the Fountain of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41504:10"/>our <hi>Tears!</hi> Alas! our cheap <hi>vulgar Weeping</hi> here, is not big enough at lowdeſt to ballance one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>Sigh</hi> of our <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s <hi>Royal Grief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We, who had ſo great a part and intereſt in her <hi>Princely Care,</hi> and <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and might have had ſo ſtill; but that our <hi>Ingratitude</hi> (that unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſin, for which we, and this poor <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> have ſo often ſmarted) our hateful <hi>Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> rendred us by ſo many degrees unworthy of her longer Life. A <hi>Bleſſing</hi> ſo infinitely deſirea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as I believe you think; that I Deſpair of add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to your preſent <hi>Information.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I'll not therefore now touch upon any <hi>Preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries;</hi> as her <hi>Royal Birth,</hi> and <hi>Deſcent;</hi> her <hi>Natural,</hi> and her <hi>Acquired Perfections,</hi> exceeding great; with her truly <hi>Chriſtian Education</hi> here, under the ſacred influence of our <hi>Dear Mother the Church</hi> of England. Which, in her, by plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt experiment, has taught us, the moſt incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Temper</hi> of her wiſe <hi>Guardiancy,</hi> and <hi>Tuition,</hi> and would make us all lovely, and belov'd as <hi>She,</hi> for th' ineſtimable <hi>Beauty</hi> of <hi>Virtuous Chriſtian Life;</hi> and would <hi>Teach</hi> our <hi>Docility</hi> not to ſhift ſo improvidently from under her <hi>Heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and <hi>pious Diſcipline;</hi> when her <hi>Spiritual Gifts</hi> are ſo many, and ſo highly advantageous,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41504:11"/>and would eaſily <hi>Bluſh,</hi> and ſhame all that unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>Prejudice,</hi> which drives ſome of us fooliſhly away, and bewilders us in a dark <hi>Superſtitious Maze</hi> of a <hi>ſtubborn forgetfulneſs</hi> of our <hi>Duties,</hi> and <hi>ourſelves.</hi> See here, and wonder! an <hi>Angelical Mind</hi> fram'd by <hi>God,</hi> and perfected into <hi>Bliſs</hi> by true <hi>Religion!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Noble <hi>Affectionate Theme</hi> wings the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt flights of our moſt grateful <hi>Thoughts;</hi> I am too weak to ſupport thus the Greatneſs of her <hi>Character;</hi> only wiſh ſincerely, that the <hi>radiant Honours</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Crown</hi> may ever Deſcend a portion to ſo <hi>Good Examples</hi> as 'twas in <hi>Royal Her,</hi> is now; and we pray, will ever be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved,</hi> you know, how we were left before their <hi>Majeſties</hi> happy <hi>Arrival</hi> joyntly in the <hi>Throne.</hi> Left ſo, that we were at a Loſs on both ſides, how to ſtate probably the reaſons of our <hi>publick welfare.</hi> Behold! a <hi>Dreadful Enemy</hi> to our <hi>Engliſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Popery</hi> on one hand, and <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> on the other: We could not be prevail'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to change our <hi>Good Religion</hi> for a <hi>worſe;</hi> and if not, we muſt part with our <hi>Property,</hi> and <hi>Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhments.</hi> 'Tis true, theſe things were not wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yet quite out of our hands, but we were throughly taught what we were to expect, by a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41504:11"/>coſtly ſad <hi>Tryal</hi> of another <hi>Neighbouring King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> before; as well as ſince, by one of our own; all this, over and above to what was miſerably indur'd in a former <hi>Reign,</hi> upon the ſame <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Principles;</hi> and however we are miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, we ſtook cloſe enough to our <hi>Paſſive O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> to the viſible <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Triumph</hi> of our <hi>Enemies,</hi> that hated us: this ſo long, 'till <hi>He,</hi> that ſhould have <hi>Govern'd</hi> us, left us, without our fault; and what reaſon we ſhould indure longer? muſt our <hi>Antient Government</hi> rot, and ſink into <hi>Ruine</hi> upon its own <hi>Foundations?</hi> It muſt certainly have done ſo, had not <hi>God</hi> ſent us, and <hi>He</hi> came, the <hi>Defender</hi> of his own Rights, and together with them, our <hi>Proteſtant Faith; William</hi> by the <hi>good Providence,</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> with his <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Conſort,</hi> whoſe Death we now <hi>Lament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Latter</hi> is my Subject more eſpecially now: Who when <hi>ſhe Landed</hi> from abroad upon the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh ſhoar,</hi> with ineſtimable <hi>Bleſſings</hi> in <hi>Her</hi> hands, to beſtow upon all but the <hi>unthankful,</hi> &amp; the <hi>evil,</hi> (tho' upon them too) <hi>She</hi> found the <hi>Nation</hi> tir'd out with <hi>Sorrow,</hi> a Leaning her weary, drooping Head on the <hi>Boſome</hi> of her <hi>Deareſt Prince,</hi> who ſurely then (if ever any one before) bad the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for our moſt ſincere <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Fidelity.</hi> And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41504:12"/>ſhe (<hi>kind, virtuous Soul</hi>) as ſhe ever lov'd to do Good, was glad to be by at hand; an <hi>Aſſiſtant,</hi> a <hi>Counſellor,</hi> and a <hi>Witneſs</hi> of our <hi>Wonderful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She</hi> found the <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp; that <hi>She</hi> lov'd the moſt in it (the <hi>Church of England</hi>) a' entring, in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy plight, the <hi>Plague</hi> of an <hi>Aegyptian Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the <hi>Land,</hi> from one corner to another, a ſwarming with <hi>Popiſh Emiſſaries;</hi> and (like the <hi>Locuſts</hi> there) darkn'd the Skye; I mean the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion full, and crowded with 'em. But, tho' ſo full, emptied much faſter than they fill'd in well nigh ſix years before, in a very ſhort time; as our day broke up again, when our <hi>Guardian Angels</hi> in conjunction, at God's immediate Direction, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd above our <hi>Horizon,</hi> with <hi>Healing</hi> in their Wings.</p>
            <p>I think, 'tis own'd on all hands, that <hi>Popery</hi> (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially as 'tis of late years refin'd by new <hi>Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Morals</hi>) is a <hi>Terror</hi> to all <hi>Proteſtant Kingdoms.</hi> As for us, we are not half ſo much afraid of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Keys<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as St. <hi>Pauls Sword;</hi> which of late (for ſome <hi>Centuries</hi> paſt) the <hi>New Church of Rome</hi> takes indifferently into her hand, with the other. We need not go far to have the footſteps of her <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty,</hi> which bleed ſo freſh in our own <hi>Annals;</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41504:12"/>tho' our <hi>Engliſh Courage</hi> has been far ever from being thought <hi>contemptible,</hi> yet we have always been very backward to Defend our <hi>Religion</hi> by ſuch <hi>Material</hi> Weapons, 'till the time, we believ'd our <hi>Lives,</hi> as well as our <hi>Conſciences</hi> were aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which, if any thing, will prove the Juſtice of our Arms; when imploy'd at the <hi>Command</hi> of our <hi>Lawful Governors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Truth</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> we modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceive we have made it good, with no ſmall advantage; and have ſhew'd abundantly, that our <hi>Church</hi> is very far from fearing any reaſonable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of that kind; having never been once outpowr'd ſince our Reformation, onely rudely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, and Diſcountenanc'd ſometimes, by <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Cruelty,</hi> and <hi>Force</hi> of <hi>Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When a <hi>Popiſh King</hi> (our late <hi>Dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi>) was ready with a Numerous, well appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Army</hi> in the Field; and our <hi>Charters,</hi> and our <hi>Properties,</hi> for a great part, <hi>Seiz'd</hi> and <hi>conſtru'd</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> and <hi>Prerogative;</hi> and a new, fine <hi>Aequivalent</hi> offer'd us, in exchange for our moſt <hi>Antient Franchiſe.</hi> Our <hi>Penal Laws</hi> to be voted down, with our <hi>Proteſtant Teſt,</hi> by a <hi>choice prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Aſſembly:</hi> when a <hi>Converſion</hi> to <hi>Popery</hi> was a currant Excuſe to other <hi>Crimes</hi> and <hi>Illegalities,</hi> it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41504:13"/>ſelf the greateſt. Execution of Good wholſome Laws generally ſuſpended; and a wide door ſet open (upon a Religious Deſign) to entertain all the <hi>Debauchery, Licentiouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm</hi> of a <hi>Wicked Age;</hi> and an unlimited Liberty tacitly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to Mens <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>Paſſions</hi> (with a very ſmall ſhare of <hi>Wit,</hi> and no <hi>Religion</hi>) to puſh on for <hi>Tumult</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> as faſt as they could. Beſides (what we don't love to remember, but cannot ſo ſoon forget) as it ſuppos'd us much more <hi>Dull</hi> and <hi>Wretched</hi> than indeed we were) injoyn us to Subſcribe (publiſh I mean) a large <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Declaration,</hi> virtually to the overthrow of our <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Religion,</hi> and all whatever elſe is ours. We <hi>bluſh'd</hi> at this time, to think, being <hi>Innocent,</hi> how we had ſo ill-deſerv'd of our <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,</hi> as to find ſo little <hi>Credit</hi> with 'em: We were (as many as obſerv'd it) extreamly ſorry at this; and that we could now <hi>Obey</hi> no longer, tho' threatn'd aloud with <hi>Penalty</hi> enough to our <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoing.</hi> We truſted in the <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion</hi> of our <hi>Good God,</hi> who Deliver'd us then, with the <hi>Reſcue</hi> of thoſe famous <hi>Confeſſors</hi> of our <hi>Sacred Hierarchy, Men of Renown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The honeſt, good, peaceable, Loyal Subject, all this while, nothing in his hand for his ſuſtenance,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41504:13"/>but a Dry unſavory Morſel of <hi>Paſſive Duty;</hi> which he had already chew'd, and Liv'd ſo long upon, that he became every day more and more naked of all other <hi>Refreſhments,</hi> and thought he was a'ſhipping ready for the ſtake of <hi>Martyrdom.</hi> When our <hi>Popiſh Governours</hi> were ſo impatient, tho' of prudent Delays; and were all for making long ſteps haſtily to our <hi>Overthrow.</hi> And, alas! our Unfortunate Monarch ſo <hi>Bigotted,</hi> and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infatuated by <hi>Jeſuited Counſels,</hi> that nor the moſt humble modeſt <hi>Complaints,</hi> nor <hi>Tears</hi> of his <hi>Faithful Subjects</hi> could prevail any thing. When <hi>Altars,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Habits</hi> appear'd openly in the <hi>Imperial City,</hi> and <hi>Countrey;</hi> and began to <hi>Neſt</hi> together in <hi>Societies;</hi> and in the name of a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King</hi> outbrav'd all, even the moſt modeſt <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of a <hi>Different Religion;</hi> and would have ſtifled, and ſuffocated all our <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and ſmother'd our Profeſſion, with an heavy indigeſted <hi>Maſs</hi> of their <hi>Exploded Forgeries,</hi> and <hi>Nonſenſe;</hi> which turn'd, upon our judicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſo much to their <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Decay,</hi> which indeed was the greateſt kindneſs they could do us, to give us <hi>opportunity</hi> thus to ſhew our <hi>ſtrength,</hi> on this manner.</p>
            <p>I would not be miſunderſtood all this while, as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41504:14"/>tho', in what I have ſaid, I ſhould ſeem the leaſt inviduous, I am forc'd to mention a little; for that our <hi>Publick Bleſſings</hi> receiv'd, cannot be duly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, without ſome competent ſence of our former <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappineſs;</hi> and undoubtedly we ſhould deſerve to be conſtru'd more than <hi>Paſſive,</hi> could we ſo ſoon forget our own <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> which is ſo plain, and dates ſo cloſe upon our <hi>Memories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Briefly then, when our <hi>Reform'd Religion,</hi> which we place ever before all other our worldly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, was in ſuch unqueſtionable, apparent Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that upon our moſt accurate <hi>Projections,</hi> all <hi>Humane</hi> means fail'd for our <hi>Deliverance;</hi> and our <hi>Misfortunes</hi> too inſpir'd, and back'd by ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent an Enemy, a <hi>Tyrant Neighbour;</hi> who upon his own ſingle <hi>ſtake,</hi> for many years together has held almoſt all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> in Play. In this <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal juncture,</hi> (by a ſtrange Miracle of the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> ſay others what they will) came the <hi>Bleſſed Pair, William</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> to our ſeaſonable reſcue; which by the ſame indulgent <hi>Providence</hi> they effected without one <hi>Drop</hi> of <hi>Blood;</hi> by a natural chearful Surrender of their own <hi>Rights</hi> into their hands; after the <hi>Royal Zealot</hi> was gone; when <hi>He</hi> had ſo unkindly <hi>Refuſed</hi> a juſt <hi>Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties;</hi> then by a <hi>general
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41504:14"/>Conſent</hi> of the <hi>Deſolate People</hi> (for how can any Kingdom ſtand without an Head to Govern it)? <hi>They</hi> the next <hi>together,</hi> in Succeſſion, are both plac'd in the <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then, and juſt before the <hi>Pride</hi> of the <hi>New Catholick Religion,</hi> and it's <hi>Empire</hi> utterly vaniſh'd; The <hi>Zealous Prieſts</hi> make haſte away; and leave their Devotion (as their Saints too of both Sexes) a'ſtarving at their <hi>Shrines:</hi> The <hi>Crafty Jeſuite</hi> packs up with the firſt, and leaves the new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts behind; aſtoniſh'd at their <hi>Religion,</hi> ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grown ſo <hi>unfaſhionable;</hi> and ſome came back to us again, aſham'd now to think their Civility carry'd them ſo far, beyond the reaſons of their <hi>Faith.</hi> But tho' theſe <hi>Holy Men</hi> left their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts</hi> here, (too few by many to raiſe a <hi>Monument</hi> to their pretended <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>Art of Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>) they forgot not to take their <hi>Riches</hi> with 'em, the <hi>vaſt Treaſure</hi> by their <hi>pious Frauds</hi> they had cheated the <hi>Nation</hi> of.</p>
            <p>Thus we of this <hi>National Church</hi> are happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd to our <hi>Religion,</hi> it's free Profeſſion; to our <hi>Properties;</hi> to our <hi>Laws;</hi> to our <hi>Liberties;</hi> to our <hi>Lives.</hi> Rid of our urgent <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> all but what the Sons of <hi>Trouble</hi> ſtudiouſly ſtrive to nurſe in their reſtleſs <hi>Boſoms.</hi> Our <hi>True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41504:15"/>has gain'd much <hi>honour,</hi> by the invincible <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> and <hi>Conſtancy</hi> of its true Profeſſors; which is <hi>God</hi>'s Cauſe, as well as our own. Our <hi>Government</hi> is re-eſtabliſh'd upon its old, beſt <hi>Foundations;</hi> and all the ſlubber of our <hi>Grief</hi> wip'd off (till now) as we lay a long time a'weeping, under the <hi>Croſs. Popery</hi> in it's <hi>inſulting Greatneſs</hi> for ever baniſh'd our <hi>Iſles.</hi> Briefly, we have loſt nothing, but what we could not keep; and hope to live as conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly as we can without; and tho' at preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in an expenſive <hi>Forreign War,</hi> we fight Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably in Defence of <hi>ourſelves,</hi> and <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi> thereby to lay (which muſt be done with time) a ſure ſtable foundation of our Security, and common Proſperity, for the future.</p>
            <p>And now, upon the foot of the Account, tell me ſeriouſly, ye <hi>Sons of Wiſdom,</hi> are not theſe I have named, <hi>Lovely</hi> great <hi>Advantages?</hi> which we owe, and confeſs (as many as are impartial) next to the good Providence of <hi>God,</hi> to the <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Vigilance</hi> of our <hi>Governors:</hi> and to <hi>Her</hi> (tho not to <hi>Her</hi> alone) whoſe Obſequies we this day Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate. <hi>She,</hi> who planted Religion both by <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> in the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> of our <hi>Government;</hi> and would have made it all of one piece, <hi>i. e. Religious;</hi> took great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41504:15"/>pains in her <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Private Devotion;</hi> and by her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent advice, and Illuſtrious <hi>Pattern</hi> taught others ſo to do, if any other, certainly a <hi>Nurſing Mother</hi> of this <hi>Church of England,</hi> which we have reaſon to think is more indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to two of our late <hi>Queens,</hi> than well-nigh all the <hi>Kings</hi> we have had till now, ſince our <hi>Happy Reformation.</hi> Good <hi>Edward</hi> liv'd but a while; and though <hi>He</hi> did as much, as 'twas poſſible for the time, being <hi>young,</hi> yet 'twas the <hi>Rudimental Beginnings only</hi> of ſo great and noble a <hi>Deſign;</hi> but what we wanted in <hi>his,</hi> was in ſome good meaſure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſated by the ſhortneſs of the next <hi>Reign;</hi> and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the happy <hi>Length</hi> of that which follow'd cloſe upon it. <hi>She</hi> who did moſt, <hi>Queen Elizabeth of ever Bleſſed Memory;</hi> the next a <hi>Peaceable Learned Prince,</hi> but came late to our <hi>Government;</hi> ſucceeded by a Son <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Wiſe;</hi> who had our <hi>Civil Diſtractions</hi> ſuffer'd him to <hi>Live,</hi> as 'twas probable otherwiſe <hi>He</hi> might, had raiſed, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd, to it's beſt advantages, our <hi>Religious Communion,</hi> as eſtabliſh'd; but ſince <hi>He</hi> could no longer ſtand, <hi>He</hi> choſe to fall a <hi>Glorious Martyr</hi> with <hi>it;</hi> and when upon our famous <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> our <hi>Regular Worſhip</hi> began again to ſmile up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us (as we did cordially upon it) it flouriſh'd, more than a little whiſe, under a <hi>Good natur'd King;</hi> 'till it was again too pitifully <hi>beclouded,</hi> in the laſt <hi>Reign,</hi> which left it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſs'd, to the more happy Succeſs and better Government of our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen;</hi> who had <hi>She</hi> longer liv'd, (as <hi>She</hi> did more than a little, in ſuch a narrow ſtint of time) ſo would have done wonderfully much more for it's <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Proſperity.</hi> But <hi>She</hi> is, alas! untimely <hi>Dead;</hi> not as to <hi>Herſelf,</hi> but us; who promis'd (as we had great reaſon) every Day more and more felicity to ourſelves, under the ſhadow of <hi>Her</hi> Government. Who, as She came with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41504:16"/>much unwillingneſs to the <hi>Throne;</hi> ſo <hi>She</hi> as willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd at <hi>Gods Command,</hi> the Burden of it, tho' by <hi>Her</hi> ſo eaſily born; and taught all <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> by her <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Example,</hi> how 'tis really practicable, and their beſt <hi>Intereſt</hi> to be <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>I have excus'd my ſelf already; give me leave but this once. Alas! Chriſtians, The <hi>Lovely Ornament</hi> of our <hi>Peace,</hi> The <hi>Beauty</hi> of our <hi>Regular Devotion,</hi> A <hi>Rare Example</hi> of <hi>Virtuous Life,</hi> The <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> the <hi>Greateſt</hi> of <hi>Her Sex,</hi> the <hi>Darling</hi> of all <hi>Her Good People,</hi> The <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Pledge</hi> of <hi>God's</hi> good <hi>Providence,</hi> our <hi>Glorious Princes</hi> is <hi>Dead,</hi> and <hi>gone.</hi> Let all our <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem weep,</hi> and <hi>Mourn</hi> for our <hi>Good Queen;</hi> as they did righteouſly for <hi>Joſiah.</hi> 'Tis indifferent, whether we Lament <hi>Her,</hi> or our <hi>Religion;</hi> they were inſeperable in <hi>Her;</hi> and how then ſhall we diſtinguiſh 'em? I cannot blame the profuſeneſs of our Grief upon this extraordinary Subject, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Venial Sin</hi> we Chriſtians can commit, ſurely this is it, the great extremity of our preſent <hi>Sorrow;</hi> and tho' we reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably conclude, this our great Concern will touch the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt heart, in the whole <hi>Nation;</hi> yet, if there be any, who cannot <hi>weep</hi> for it, and us; I hope, without injury, we may take leave to <hi>weep</hi> for ourſelves and <hi>them.</hi> 'Twere well the reaſons of our <hi>Sorrow</hi> were not real, as we believe they are, upon <hi>impartial view.</hi> Tho' yet we are not in the leaſt unthankful; but know how to <hi>prize</hi> all the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> we have left behind; our <hi>Good King,</hi> and <hi>Royal Family.</hi> But theſe all <hi>Mourn</hi> as well as we; and we humbly think we have as great a cauſe as any; tho' all this we know is fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and in vain. But how can tender hearts expreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their <hi>paſſionate reſentments,</hi> in a milder way? not that we ſhould ſeem fondly envy <hi>Her</hi> her <hi>Happineſs</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41504:16"/>above, who ſtood ever the faireſt <hi>Candidate</hi> for an <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Crown:</hi> But we beg leave here thus to acknowledge, and confeſs our <hi>many obligations;</hi> and to embalm, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve her <hi>Sacred Memory</hi> to perpetual Generations, with the <hi>Deareſt</hi> expreſſions of our moſt unfeigned <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I fear I have held you too long in this <hi>Melancholly Scene;</hi> I have done then; only mind you very briefly of two things, to which our preſent <hi>Affliction</hi> ſeems nigheſt ally'd. The reaſons, I mean, that lye uppermoſt to our knowledge, and are moſt Legible, in ſuch an harſh Providence as this is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either by this ſort of <hi>Diſcipline, God</hi> in his infinite wiſdom, has a mind to mean us, from an over fondneſs, we are too apt to create to ourſelves of any <hi>Humane Help,</hi> we think ſtands nigheſt our <hi>Temporal Happineſs;</hi> and then 'twill teach us <hi>Patience.</hi> Thus, we know, He exerciſed the <hi>People</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> when under th' immediate <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> of his <hi>Theocracy</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and after when they were <hi>embodied,</hi> and had <hi>Kings,</hi> as th'other <hi>Nations;</hi> depriving 'em of <hi>Succeſs</hi> oftimes by many ſecret methods of his good Providence; thereby to hold 'em the cloſer to himſelf in their <hi>Dependence,</hi> and the Counſel of his own <hi>Divine Will;</hi> who has many more ways for our Succour, in the unerring <hi>Conduct</hi> of his <hi>Eternal Wiſdom,</hi> than we can imagine. Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. God puniſhes us thus <hi>ſeverely</hi> for our manifold abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſins, as <hi>He</hi> did the <hi>Jews</hi> oftimes; particularly here in the matter of <hi>Joſiah;</hi> and then <hi>Mourning</hi> is the leaſt part of what we have to do, which concerns us moſt in a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Reformation</hi> of our <hi>Wicked Lives;</hi> leſt otherwiſe, upon our continued <hi>provocations,</hi> our <hi>Judgment,</hi> as it proceeds from the <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> ſhould thus conclude our <hi>Good King</hi> too, whom God long preſerve, with th'other <hi>Royal Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41504:17"/>this needs every good, ſober Chriſtians conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Finally: If our <hi>Grief</hi> be real upon the ſence of our great <hi>Loſs,</hi> it ſuppoſes we underſtand the worth of <hi>Good Princes;</hi> and conſequently, (as we now Mourn for <hi>Her,</hi> whoſe <hi>Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Day</hi> we celebrate, ſo) we, from henceforth, apply our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all dutiful, and <hi>Loyal Love,</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> to <hi>Him</hi> who is now in the <hi>Throne;</hi> and to this good end, ſhun and diſencourage, the moſt we can, in ourſelves and others, all <hi>cauſeleſs Jealouſies,</hi> and <hi>turbulent Counſels;</hi> which, in the effect, ſhould any way cool, and diminiſh from our <hi>cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Obedience;</hi> and learn to ſubmit ourſelves <hi>Dutifully</hi> to our <hi>Governors,</hi> as well as to <hi>Pray</hi> for 'em; That <hi>God</hi> would grant our <hi>King</hi> a long, and an happy <hi>Reign</hi> over us: and that <hi>we,</hi> and all his <hi>Subjects</hi> (duly conſidering whoſe <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> he hath) may faithfully ſerve, honour, and humbly obey <hi>Him,</hi> according to <hi>God's Holy Word,</hi> and <hi>Ordinance;</hi> and that <hi>He</hi> may ever ſtudy to <hi>Preſerve</hi> thy <hi>People,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Charge, in <hi>Wealth, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Goodlineſs.</hi> Grant this, O <hi>Merciful Father,</hi> for thy <hi>Dear Sons</hi> ſake <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> our <hi>Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
